<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: General | flickr downloadr]]></title>
  <link href="http://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-27T14:17:09-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[flickr downloadr]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello, World!]]></title>
    <link href="http://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/blog/2013/01/07/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-07T20:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/blog/2013/01/07/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h4>Hello, and a hearty welcome to the flickr downloadr blog!</h4>

<p><a href="/../">flickr downloadr</a> was conceived back in May 2012 when I surprisingly discovered that even with the awesome <a href="http://www.flickr.com/services/api/">API</a> that flickr provides there are no free and/or open source app that lets one download their photos <em>along with the metadata</em>. I also wanted to learn the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms754130.aspx" title="Windows Presentation Foundation">WPF</a> and <strong>flickr downloadr</strong> was born.</p>

<p>But soon after the authentication modules using <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OAuth" title="OAuth">OAuth</a> were done, the enthusiasm died and there was a brief hiatus in the development and it is recently that it has gained some momentum again. As of this writing, the latest beta version of the app works on any version of Windows that can run <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/w0x726c2.aspx">.NET framework 4.5</a>, which is Windows Vista (untested), Windows 7 and Windows 8.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are quite a few rough edges and a few known issues, but when signed in with a flickr <a href="http://www.flickr.com/help/limits/#28">Pro</a> (read <em>paid</em>) account, the app would show all of the photos from the logged in user&rsquo;s photostream. All of the photos, or a selection could then be downloaded and again, as of the version of this writing (v0.6.3.1), the location where photos are downloaded, the size, and the associated metadata are all hard-coded.</p>

<p>In the coming months, the plan is to add a way to capture user preferences for some of the things mentioned above and also to fix the few known bugs/defects.</p>

<p>If you are windows user who has a Pro account on flickr, please <a href="/../downloads/latest">download and install</a> the app and let me know your comments/suggestions. If you are .NET/WPF developer and/or an open source enthusiast, please checkout the <a href="https://github.com/flickr-downloadr/flickr-downloadr">source over at GitHub</a> and leave your comments/suggestions/criticisms on the code.</p>

<p>Thanks. And have a beautiful day !</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
