<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cross Platform | flickr downloadr]]></title>
  <link href="https://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/blog/categories/cross-platform/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/"/>
  <updated>2024-01-28T18:59:55-05:00</updated>
  <id>https://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[flickr downloadr]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Batch download flickr photos from Windows, Mac or Linux!]]></title>
    <link href="https://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/blog/2014/06/12/batch-download-flickr-photos-from-windows-mac-or-linux/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-12T00:34:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>https://flickrdownloadr.com/blogs/blog/2014/06/12/batch-download-flickr-photos-from-windows-mac-or-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="/blog/2014/01/20/contemplating-a-mac-port-of-flickr-downloadr/">previous entry</a> on this blog discussed the idea of probably creating a native, Cocoa, Mac OS X port for the then, Windows-only, WPF version of the app.</p>

<p>Any action started much later from the date of the post; to be precise, more than two months later with the creation of a new repository with <a href="https://github.com/flickr-downloadr/flickr-downloadr-gtk/commit/3f94a6bc13c87f905e3f5be5e9872accb6930f05">this commit</a>. The research that happened in-between helped decide on a third alternative - that of completely porting over the .NET C#/WPF into a Mono, C#/GTK# app that could work on all of Windows, Mac and Linux.</p>

<p>And exactly after two months and one day <a href="https://github.com/flickr-downloadr/flickr-downloadr-gtk/commit/de399a3526344ea96d1847eff2836e15674a7553">the v1.0</a> of the new GTKSharp enabled flickr downloadr was published on <a href="/../">this website</a>.</p>

<p>It really was an exhilarating journey of many frustrations, joy, learnings and moments of bliss - and there are a few things that I would like to follow up in separate entries here. Like:</p>

<ol>
<li>the parallel, multi-platform continuous integration/deployment that happens on <a href="https://ci.appveyor.com/project/floydpink/flickr-downloadr-gtk">AppVeyor (Windows)</a>, <a href="https://travis-ci.org/flickr-downloadr/flickr-downloadr-gtk">Travis CI (Mac)</a> and <a href="https://app.wercker.com/#applications/5363d07d2cbfc1b354003e84">Wercker (Linux)</a>.</li>
<li>the building of a cross-platform installer using the free-for-open-source Enterprise edition of <a href="http://installbuilder.bitrock.com/">Install Builder</a> provided generously by the awesome guys at BitRock.</li>
<li>the slight face-lift applied on the website along with the cut-over to a new, <a href="http://yeoman.io/">Yeoman</a> scaffolded web-app - complete with its automated <code>grunt</code> build for minification, image compression etc. (do a quick <em>View Source</em> on this page to see the results)</li>
</ol>


<p>&hellip;and many other such learnings and experiences.</p>

<p>So, please spread the word of this new, free, open-source utility for batch downloading photos from flickr that is available on Windows, Mac OS X and Linux (Ubuntu &amp; Mint have been tested).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
